<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Photography | Adam Caudill]]></title>
  <link href="https://adamcaudill.com//categories/photography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://adamcaudill.com//"/>
  <updated>2015-11-19T00:41:18-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://adamcaudill.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Adam Caudill]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lumix DMC-FZ8 & Infrared]]></title>
    <link href="https://adamcaudill.com//2009/06/21/lumix-dmc-fz8-infrared/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-21T17:35:10-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://adamcaudill.com//2009/06/21/lumix-dmc-fz8-infrared</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After several months of tests and experiments, I have finally determined something: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infrared_photography">Infrared</a> with the Lumix <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/news/0701/07013106panasonicfz8.asp">DMC-FZ8</a> just doesn't work.
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/adamcaudill/2789422097"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/adamcaudill/2789422097"><img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3184/2789422097_5bdc2f0d88_m.jpg" alt="Early IR Test" /></a></p>

<p>I've been trying to use a <a href="http://www.jpgmag.com/stories/71">R72</a> Near-Infrared filter to filter out the "normal" light that we see, leaving only the infrared light that I wanted to capture. The FZ8 is sensitive to infrared, as can be easily demonstrated by taking a picture of a TV remote control. What you'll see is a couple points of light coming from the remote; these are the infrared lights that are used to transmit commands to the TV.</p>

<p>Though having a camera that is sensitive to infrared, doesn't make it suited for infrared photography. While the FZ8 is a great camera, being light weight, offering pro-level options (such as RAW mode) without the bulk of a DSLR - this is one thing that just doesn't work.</p>

<p>Here are a few of the issues I've seen, and so far been unable to get passed:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Auto-Focus: While this isn't a huge surprise, auto-focus doesn't work when the R72 filter is in place.</p></li>
<li><p>Manual-Focus: The FZ8 does offer manual focus, though using it when there is so little light making it to the sensor is nearly impossible.</p></li>
<li><p>Grainy: Even when ISO is set to 100 instead of the default of auto, the images are extremely grainy. While this can provide a somewhat artistic effect - it's not what I'm looking for.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>While it does seem to have some promise in replicating an infrared version of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinhole_camera">pinhole photography</a>, it simply doesn't work for traditional infrared.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
