<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Development | Adam Caudill]]></title>
  <link href="https://adamcaudill.com//categories/development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://adamcaudill.com//"/>
  <updated>2015-11-19T00:22:32-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://adamcaudill.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Adam Caudill]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CCSRCH v1.0.7]]></title>
    <link href="https://adamcaudill.com//2012/02/29/ccsrch-v1-0-7/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-29T23:47:17-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://adamcaudill.com//2012/02/29/ccsrch-v1-0-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've released a new version of <a href="https://github.com/adamcaudill/ccsrch">CCSRCH</a>, the open-source PAN (a.k.a credit card number) search tool to help companies maintain PCI compliance. This is a fairly minor release, primarily focusing on reducing false positives. The scanner has been updated to exclude the following:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Results made up of the same two digits repeating (i.e. 5454545454545454).</p></li>
<li><p>Results that have seven or more of the same digits repeating (i.e. 5555555555554444).</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I also fixed a bug that I introduced in v1.0.6 that prevented it from compiling on certain *nix systems; while I was in there I also fixed several instances of this building warning on newer Linux distros:</p>

<pre><code>warning: call to __builtin___strncat_chk might overflow destination buffer
 [enabled by default]
</code></pre>

<p>I also took the time to write-up really simple build instructions for *nix users:</p>

<pre><code>$ wget -O ccsrch.tar.gz https://github.com/adamcaudill/ccsrch/tarball/master
$ tar -xvzf ccsrch.tar.gz
$ cd adamcaudill-ccsrch-&lt;rev&gt;/
$ make all
</code></pre>

<p>This will probably be the last release for now unless a bug turns up; to improve results further I'm working on a new project (<a href="https://github.com/adamcaudill/ccsrch-score">ccsrch-score</a>), hopefully it'll be released soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Cringely is wrong about Java]]></title>
    <link href="https://adamcaudill.com//2011/10/15/why-cringely-is-wrong-about-java/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-15T15:47:52-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://adamcaudill.com//2011/10/15/why-cringely-is-wrong-about-java</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of days ago I was sent a link to Robert Cringely's latest treatise:  <em><a href="http://www.cringely.com/2011/10/the-second-coming-of-java/">The second coming of Java</a></em> - and to say I disagreed was a bit of an understatement. To me, it represents a fundamental flaw in his perception of developers, and more importantly the economics of software development.</p>

<p>The key to Cringely's argument comes down to this:</p>

<p>When SSDs gain enough capacity there will be a shift from the Ruby world back to the Java world. Not for prototyping, because, well, it’s prototyping. But simply because the statement “<strong>Ruby is <em>incredibly</em> slow but I don’t care because my database is slower</strong>” will no longer be true.</p>

<p>What he's missing here is the real reason people use frameworks like Rails; it's not about it being Ruby, or being the latest cool thing - it's about developer productivity. That's it, and that's all there is to it - Rails allows a developer to do more in less time. That's one of the key reasons so many Java web developers jumped ship (though I can think of a few others), and what pushed Microsoft to invest so heavily in their <a href="http://www.asp.net/mvc">MVC framework</a>.</p>

<p>I could fully rehash the argument, but in what I consider to be one of Jeff Atwood's best articles,  <em><a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2008/12/hardware-is-cheap-programmers-are-expensive.html">Hardware is Cheap, Programmers are Expensive</a></em>, he covers a key point to my argument - developer time is vastly more expensive than hardware. Atwood's take on the issue is clear:</p>

<p>Clearly, <strong>hardware is cheap, and programmers are expensive</strong>. Whenever you're provided an opportunity to leverage that imbalance, it would be incredibly foolish not to.</p>

<p>When there's a choice between developer productivity, and spending money on hardware - the conclusion should be the same. It's much cheaper to throw more hardware at a slower framework than it is to invest more developer time in a faster framework. For any non-trivial application, throwing more front-end servers at it will always be cheaper than slowing the development process down with a non-productivity-centric toolkit.</p>

<p>It's simple economics; server hardware is getting faster and cheaper, developer time is only getting more expensive.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy 20th birthday Visual Basic!]]></title>
    <link href="https://adamcaudill.com//2011/05/21/happy-20th-birthday-visual-basic/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-21T01:50:19-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://adamcaudill.com//2011/05/21/happy-20th-birthday-visual-basic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I saw a post on Facebook by a friend of mine, <a href="http://inotifythoughtschanging.net/blog/">Anthony Green</a>, about writing his first blog post as a Microsoft employee (he has a personal blog as well, unfortunately he's not written anything since 2008) - when I saw the title, I couldn't believe it was 20 years already - seems just yesterday that I wrote about its <a href="http://adamcaudill.com/2006/05/27/happy-belated-birthday-vb/">15th birthday</a>:</p>

<p><a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/vbteam/archive/2011/05/20/happy-20th-birthday-visual-basic.aspx">Happy 20th Birthday Visual Basic!</a></p>

<p>My, what a journey it's been. Almost fifteen years ago I randomly bought a copy of "Visual Basic 5: Deluxe Learning Edition" - I was just 15 at the time and wanted a new hobby, and writing software seemed like it would be fun. In those early days, I had no idea what career I would choose, and really didn't intend for software development to become the dominant force in my life - I just wanted a better, more productive way to spend my time during the summer.</p>

<p>In the years that have went by, I became passionate about the field, and all it encompasses (possible obsessed, if you believe my wife) - it's been the driving force in my life. Today, I manage a team of 6 developers, and have a fun start-up with some friends (that someday won't cost me money every month) - and all because I bought that book. Overall, I have a lot to thank VB for, it really did get me started in this field.</p>

<p>Today though, my language of choice has moved on to newer options - I prefer bleeding technologies when I can use them - but VB will always have a place in my heart, and I'll always follow its progress as it continues to transform and adapt to an ever-changing world. As the most popular .NET language (contrary to what many of the C# developers think), it plays a vital role in the development of the framework and the ecosystem.</p>

<p>In the conversations I've had with Anthony about the future of the language, I greatly look forward to writing about its 25th birthday; I expect those will be exciting times for the language and the entire .NET ecosystem.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[VB6: Not so open source]]></title>
    <link href="https://adamcaudill.com//2011/05/20/vb6-not-so-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-20T02:33:23-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://adamcaudill.com//2011/05/20/vb6-not-so-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Earlier today, a rather surprising tweet hit, being retweeted at least 80 times, including by a few rather influential people in the .NET world:</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" align="center"><p>Microsoft announces to mvps at <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23msteched">#msteched</a> that VB6 will be released as open source on codeplex end of june! w00t</p>&mdash; Roy Osherove (@RoyOsherove) <a href="https://twitter.com/RoyOsherove/status/71287262842859520">May 19, 2011</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>Needless to say, that's not an announcement that anybody was expecting, but given the talk going on at the time - and the high-profile people talking about it, there wasn't much reason to doubt. Announcing a product that has been dead for years is going open source would certainly be a strategy shift for Microsoft, but does it make any sense? <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/kevindente">Kevin Dente</a> of <a href="http://herdingcode.com/">Herding Code</a> fame certainly thought that Microsoft had better things to release:</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" align="center"><p>Instead of VB6 I'd rather see MS open source IE6. Then at least we could build a standalone version of it.</p>&mdash; Kevin Dente (@kevindente) <a href="https://twitter.com/kevindente/status/71292995185553408">May 19, 2011</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>Shortly after the initial tweet, <a href="http://www.dougseven.com/">Doug Seven</a>, the Director of Product Management, Visual Studio Tools &amp; Languages, <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/dseven/status/71316722854002688">replied</a> asking Roy Osherove (the original poster) to email him. Hmm, it's starting to smell like something odd is going on. A couple of hours later, Doug set the story straight:</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" align="center"><p>The rumors of VB6 going open source are simply not true. <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23msteched">#msteched</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23vb6rumor">#vb6rumor</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23vb6">#vb6</a></p>&mdash; dseven (@dseven) <a href="https://twitter.com/dseven/status/71352709785198592">May 19, 2011</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>To which, Roy then tried to unset:</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" align="center"><p>RT @<a href="https://twitter.com/dseven">dseven</a>: The rumors of VB6 going open source are true. <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23msteched">#msteched</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23vb6rumor">#vb6rumor</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23vb6">#vb6</a></p>&mdash; Roy Osherove (@RoyOsherove) <a href="https://twitter.com/RoyOsherove/status/71355603611680769">May 19, 2011</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>It's worth pointing out that Roy Osherove currently has a full ten-times the followers that Doug Seven has, meaning his altered retweet was seen by more people (at least initially). For several hours word was going around, and accepted by a number of people who thought Microsoft was actually going to open the code to VB6 (including journalists who were too busy writing articles to do any fact checking) - all based on one person who made it all up.</p>

<p>Lesson here: be careful about what you re-tweet, it's easy to endorse a lie as several people unwittingly did today (<a href="http://twitter.com/#!/blowdart">@blowdart</a> summed it <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/blowdart/status/71370740934524928">rather well</a>).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Errors on 'gem install mysql2']]></title>
    <link href="https://adamcaudill.com//2011/05/16/errors-on-gem-install-mysql2/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-16T01:29:19-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://adamcaudill.com//2011/05/16/errors-on-gem-install-mysql2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On my fresh Ubuntu 11.04 box running Ruby 1.9.2 instead of the standard Ruby 1.8, I ran into some undocumented errors while installing the <code>mysql2</code> gem. Here's what I was seeing:</p>

<pre><code>$ gem install mysql2
Building native extensions.  This could take a while...
ERROR:  Error installing mysql2:
    ERROR: Failed to build gem native extension.

        /usr/bin/ruby1.9.1 extconf.rb
          &lt;internal:lib/rubygems/custom_require&gt;:29:in `require': 
          no such file to load -- mkmf (LoadError)
    from &lt;internal:lib/rubygems/custom_require&gt;:29:in `require'
    from extconf.rb:2:in `&lt;main&gt;'


Gem files will remain installed in 
  /usr/lib/ruby/gems/1.9.1/gems/mysql2-0.3.2 for inspection.
Results logged to 
  /usr/lib/ruby/gems/1.9.1/gems/mysql2-0.3.2/ext/mysql2/gem_make.out
</code></pre>

<p>This obviously isn't all that helpful, nor did I find anything all that useful on Google - thankfully the issue is easy to solve. All that's needed is to ensure that the following packages are installed:</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install libmysqlclient-dev libmysql-ruby1.9 ruby1.9.1-dev
</code></pre>

<p>Then you can try installing the gem, it should work, hopefully</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
